Hello,
the California Department of Motor Vehicles has a unique unit that focuses
on the needs and concerns of senior drivers and their families.
It's called the Senior Driver Ombudsman and Outreach Unit,
and it's staffed with dedicated DMV representatives who are
committed to helping senior drivers maintain their driving independence.
After all,
we know
that mobility matters.
Our team makes sure that senior drivers are treated with dignity,
respect,
and fairly
consistent with our laws and regulations.
We do that by offering outreach seminars for large and small audiences.
I'll be providing you with some contact numbers in just a little bit.
Our team also assists with individual cases that deal with public safety,
sort of a go-between to resolve DMV issues.
We want to keep seniors driving for as long as they can do so safely.
In fact,
research has shown that senior drivers are some of
the safest drivers on our roads and highways.
California law requires drivers who are 70 years of age or older
to renew their driver's license in person when it expires.
Here's what you can expect when you visit a DMV office.
You'll need to take a short 18 question driver knowledge exam,
pass a vision examination.
And have a new picture taken for your driver's license.
You'll have to repeat this process every 5 years.
Again,
this is a state law and not a DMV mandate.
We know that as we get older,
our reflexes slow down and we may experience issues with our vision.
These types of physical changes can put you and other drivers at risk.
If you find yourself in this position.
You may be asked to come back to our office for a re-examination.
Generally,
law enforcement,
medical professionals,
family and friends submit these types of requests.
The DMV then investigates to evaluate your level of risk.
You also may be asked to provide medical information
and take a knowledge exam and a driving test.
Now,
if your medical condition impacts your mobility,
you may be able to apply for a disabled person parking placard.
They're available to both drivers and passengers,
and they can only be used when the person to whom it's assigned is inside the vehicle.
That means it's illegal to lend it to a family member or a friend,
use someone else's,
or alter a placard or placard identification card.
To request a placard,
you need to complete an application.
Which includes a section that requires a
licensed medical professional to complete and sign.
These placards are honored in all 50 states.
Right now,
permanent placards are automatically renewed every 2 years,
but beginning in June 2023,
placard holders will need to submit a renewal notice every 6 years.
A medical certification is not required.
Required.
Temporary placards are also available and valid up to 6 months.
You can find more information on the DMV website
at DMV.C.gov.
Overall,
seniors are responsible drivers.
They're constantly monitoring their health,
assessing their driving abilities,
and evaluating when it's time to stop driving.
We recommend that seniors discuss this transition with family and friends
and develop a plan
on how to move around and remain as independent as possible.
There are several options you should investigate.
You may want to find out if there's a paratransit service in your area,
identify public transportation and ride share companies.
Reach out to senior centers
and check if family and friends may be able to offer you a lift.
Don't forget that many grocery stores and pharmacies offer delivery service,
medications can be ordered by mail,
and you can also shop online.
Now if you're concerned about the driving ability
of a family member or someone you know,
it's very important to approach this issue with compassion.
Now you may feel frustrated and even guilty
about depriving someone of their freedom to drive,
but remain positive
and supportive.
Older drivers may think that authorities,
friends,
or relatives are out to get them,
and that's why it's important to be
sensitive about how you start this conversation.
And remember,
age alone should not be a basis for limiting someone's driving privilege
or taking it away.
You can find more information in the DMV senior guide for safe driving,
which is available on our website,
DMV.C.gov.
We also offer video tutorials to help you brush up on your driving skills.
Just click the YouTube icon that you find at the bottom of our home page.
Here are some other helpful resources.
AARP offers a mature driving program.
AAA
has a car fit program
to help your personal vehicle fit you better,
and you may want to check with the CHP about its Drive Smart classes.
And as promised earlier,
here's how you can contact our DMV senior driver ombudsman and outreach unit.
If you live in Southern California,
call 310-615-3552.
In Northern California,
the number is 916-657-6464.
DME representatives are available to participate in outreach seminars
to promote driver safety in California
with an emphasis
on senior concerns.
Did you know by the year 2030,
an estimated 1 in 5 drivers in the United States will be 65 years or older?
Well,
that's why the California DMV will continue to work with our seniors
to maintain their driving independence for as long as they can do so safely.